# **Chuck Pepe-Ranney**

**Data Scientist** 

Durham, NC

Data Scientist with extensive DevOps, genomics, and data visualization experience. I have programmed in Python for over ten years and R for over six. I make sense of complex data using modern data science tools, cloud technology, and domain expertise.

## Experience



## Data Scientist and Data Science Group Leader

2016-present

AgBiome

I designed and led the development of AgBiome's AWS Genomics Data Platform.

I developed the cloud-based infrastructure and data scientist developer tooling to write and deploy data-driven monitoring and real-time analytics dashboards.

I wrote (first author) AgBiome's first peer-reviewed scientific publication. The Phytobiomes Journal awarded our manuscript with the "Editor's Pick" distinction.

## Adjunct Faculty Instructor

2019-present

University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill—Gillings School of Public Health
I teach the Data Science Basics course (BIOS512) in the Gillings School of Global Public Health
at UNC. The course covers professional data transformation, preparation, and visualization
using the R programming language and Tidy Data principles.

#### Postdoctoral Researcher and Research Associate

2013-2016

Cornell University; Ithaca, NY

I designed and applied a microbiome analysis pipeline for DNA-SIP-based microbial ecology studies of agricultural soils and biological soil crusts.

As first author I published several manuscripts in refereed journals and contributed as a coauthor to many additional scientific publications.

#### **Teaching Fellow Microbial Diversity Course, Four Summers**

2010-2014

Marine Biology Laboratory, Woods Hole

I taught data analysis best practices in microbiome science focusing on the QIIME and Mothur toolkits and molecular biology laboratory techniques. I also administered the course Linux servers.

#### SULI Undergraduate Researcher, Two Summers

2005-2006

Idaho National Laboratory

Two summers studying thermophilic microoragnisms at INL.

Awarded SULI undergraduate scholarship.

## Education



## PhD, Environmental Science and Engineering Division

2009-2013

Colorado School of Mines

### M.S. Environmental Engineering

2007-2009

Colorado School of Mines

Biotechnology and Environmental Microbiology emphasis

#### B.S. Engineering, Environmental Science Specialty

2002-2006

Colorado School of Mines

**High Honors** 

Outstanding Graduating Senior Award, 2006

updated on: Wed Oct 07 2020

## **SKILLS**

**Python** 

R

JavaScript/D3js

**SQL** 

**AWS** 

Docker

HTML/CSS/SVG

Bash

Linux

## LINKS

♦ chuckpr.github.io

github.com/chuckpr

**G** Google Scholar

in linkedin.com/in/chuckpr

#### CONTACT

□ 575-313-0993

@ chuck.peperanney@gmail

- Pepe-Ranney, C; Keyser, C; Trimble, JK; Bissinger, B, Surveying the sweetpotato rhizosphere, endophyte, and surrounding soil microbiomes at two North Carolina farms reveals underpinnings of sweetpotato microbiome community assembly 2020 Phytobiomes Journal (Awarded Editor's Pick distinction)
- Jackson, EW; Pepe-Ranney, C; Johnson, MR; Distel, DL; Hewson, I, A highly prevalent and pervasive densovirus discovered
  among sea stars from the North American Atlantic Coast 2020 Applied and Environmental Microbiology
- Roco, CA; Dörsch, P; Booth, JG; Pepe-Ranney, C; Groffman, PM; Fahey, TJ; Yavitt, JB; Shapleigh, JP, Using metagenomics to
  reveal landscape scale patterns of denitrifiers in a montane forest ecosystem 2019 Soil Biology and Biochemistry
- Jackson, EW; Pepe-Ranney, C; Debenport, SJ; Buckley, DH; Hewson, I, The microbial landscape of sea stars and the
  anatomical and interspecies variability of their microbiome 2018 Frontiers in Microbiology
- Choudoir, MJ; Pepe-Ranney, C; Buckley, DH, Diversification of secondary metabolite biosynthetic gene clusters coincides with lineage divergence in Streptomyces 2018 Antibiotics
- Whitman, T; Pepe-Ranney, C; Enders, A; Koechli, C; Campbell, A; Buckley, DH; Lehmann, J, Dynamics of microbial community
  composition and soil organic carbon mineralization in soil following addition of pyrogenic and fresh organic matter
  2016 ISMEJ
- Pepe-Ranney, C\*; Campbell, AN\*; Koechli, CN; Berthrong, S; Buckley, DH, Unearthing the ecology of soil microorganisms
  using a high resolution DNA-SIP approach to explore cellulose and xylose metabolism in soil 2016 Frontiers in
  Microbiology (\*co-first authors)
- Pepe-Ranney, C; Koechli, C; Potrafka, R; Andam, C; Eggleston, E; Garcia-Pichel, F; Buckley, DH, Non-cyanobacterial diazotrophs mediate dinitrogen fixation in biological soil crusts during early crust formation. 2015 ISMEJ
- Pepe-Ranney, C; Hall, EK, The effect of carbon subsidies on marine planktonic niche partitioning and recruitment during biofilm assembly 2015 Frontiers in Microbiology
- Wallace, BD; Roberts, AB; Pollet, RM; Ingle, JD; Biernat, KA; Pellock, SJ; Venkatesh, MK; Guthrie, L; O'Neal, SK; Robinson, SJ; Dollinger, M; Figueroa, E; McShane, SR; Cohen, RD; Jin, J; Frye, SV; Zamboni, WC; Pepe-Ranney, C; Mani, S; Kelly, L; Redinbo1, MR, Structure and inhibition of microbiome β-glucuronidases essential to the alleviation of cancer drug toxicity 2015 Chemistry & Biology
- Bräuer, SL; Vuono, D; Carmichael, MJ; Pepe-Ranney, C; Strom, A; Rabinowitz, E; Buckley, DH; Zinder, SH, Microbial sequencing analyses suggest the presence of a fecal veneer on indoor climbing wall holds 2014 Current Microbiology
- Pepe-Ranney, C; Berelson, WM; Corsetti, FA; Treants, M; Spear, JR, Cyanobacterial construction of hot spring siliceous stromatolites in Yellowstone National Park 2012 Environmental Microbiology
- Osburn, MR; Sessions, AL; Pepe-Ranney, C; Spear, JR, Hydrogen-isotopic variability in fatty acids from Yellowstone
   National Park hot spring microbial communities 2011 Geochimica et Cosmochimica Acta
- Berelson, WM; Corsetti, FA; Pepe-Ranney, C; Hammond, DE; Beaumont, W; Spear, JR, Hot spring siliceous stromatolites from Yellowstone National Park: assessing growth rate and laminae formation 2011 Geobiology

### Invited Talks



- **50,000 Genomes and counting: how to manage and explore the data from your giant collection of microbial isolates** 2018

  New Frontiers in Plant Biology Workshop CBGP-Madrid
- **40,000+ Genomes and counting: Computational lessons from building a giant culture collection** 2017 AIChE (American Institute of Chemical Engineers): Microbial communities and microbiomes for agriculture and bioenergy session
- Tracking carbon into and through the soil microbial community with DNA-SIP 2016 EcoFAB Workshop Joint Genome Institute
- Leveraging analytics: Putting big data to good use 2016 Ag Biotech Professional Forum North Carolina Biotechnology Center Targeting unknowns just underfoot: Microbial ecology and community genomics of C cycling in soil informed and enabled with DNA-SIP 2015 American Geophysical Union Fall Meeting: Understanding microbial processes, dependencies, and impacts through 'omics session
- Cyanobacterial construction of finely laminated siliceous stromatolites in a Yellowstone National Park hot spring 2012

  Astrobiology Science Conference: Microbes in lithifying systems session
- 14C and microbial diversity study of Yellowstone siliceous stromatolites: searching for the depositional community 2009 Microbiology Supergroup Meeting MCDB University of Colorado Boulder